<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The proceedings of the High Court of Iustice with Charls Stuart, late King of England, in Westminster Hall, begun January 20. ended Ianuary 27, 1648: together with his speech on the scaffold at his execution at Whitehall gate, Jan. 30. 1648. Whereunto is added his prayers in the time of his sufferings: and also, his speeches to his chi[l]dren; with a letter from the Prince. Together with his reasons against the jurisdiction of the High court of Iustice, which he intended to delive[r] in writing on Munday, Jan. 22. 1648.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55956</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831936</idno>
  <idno type="VID">36403</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240940384</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3587</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220540</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831936</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831936e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55956)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36403)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2054:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The proceedings of the High Court of Iustice with Charls Stuart, late King of England, in Westminster Hall, begun January 20. ended Ianuary 27, 1648: together with his speech on the scaffold at his execution at Whitehall gate, Jan. 30. 1648. Whereunto is added his prayers in the time of his sufferings: and also, his speeches to his chi[l]dren; with a letter from the Prince. Together with his reasons against the jurisdiction of the High court of Iustice, which he intended to delive[r] in writing on Munday, Jan. 22. 1648.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 118, 120-121, 121-138 p., plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for VV.B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes with caption title: Prayers used by His Maiesty, in the time of His sufferings.  Pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Copy catalogued imperfect; pp. 81-84 and pp. 105-108 have been replaced with blank pages; text is not continuous.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; pages cropped and stained with some loss of text. The "l" in "children" failed to print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Death and burial --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Last words --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36403:1"/>
            <p>THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE High Court of Iustice, With <hi>CHARLS STƲART,</hi> late King of <hi>England,</hi> in Westminster Hall, Begun January 20. ended Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary 27, 1648:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with his Speech on the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fold at his Execution at Whitehall gate, Jan.</hi> 30. 1648.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added his prayers in the time of his sufferings: And also, his Speeches to his chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dren; with a Letter from the <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with his Reasons against the Jurisdiction of the High court of Iustice, which he intended to deliver in writing on Munday, <hi>Jan.</hi> 22. 1648.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>VV. B.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:36403:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Aetatis suae</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:36403:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:36403:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36403:3"/>
            <head>The first dayes proceedings of the High Court of Justice, in the Tryal of <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in the great hall in <hi>Westminster, Jan.</hi> 20. 1648.</head>
            <p>ON Saturday, being the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>January</hi> 1648. The Lord <hi>Bradshaw</hi> President of the High Court of Justice, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> neer fourscore of the Members of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> said Court, having sixteen Gentlemen with Partizans, and a Sword, and a Mace, with their, and other Officers of the said Court, marching before them, came to the place ordered to be prepared for their sitting, at the West end of the great Hall in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inster,</hi> where the Lord President in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rimson Velvet Chair, fixed in the midst of the Court, placed himself, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Desk with a Crimson Velvet Cus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n before him; The rest of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36403:4"/> Members placing themselves on each side of him upon the severall Seats, or Benches, prepared and hung with Scarlet for that purpose, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizans dividing themselves on each side of the Court before them:</p>
            <p>The Court being thus set, and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence made, the great Gate of the said Hall was set open to the end, That all persons, without exception, desirous to see, or hear, might come into it, upon which the Hall was presently filled, and silence again ordered.</p>
            <p>This done Collonel <hi>Thomlinson</hi> who had the charge of the Prisoner, was commanded to bring him to the Court, who within a quarter of an hours space brought him attended with about twenty Officers with Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizans marching before him, there being other Gentlemen, to whose care and custody he was likewise com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, marching in his Rear.</p>
            <p>Being thus brought up within the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36403:4"/> face of the Court, the Serjeant at Arms, with his Mace, receives and conducts him straight to the B r, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a crimson velvet Chair set before him. After a stern looking upon the Court, and the people in the Galleries on each side of him, he places himself, not at at all moving his ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise shewing the least respect, to the Court; but presently rises up again, and turns about, looking downwards upon the Guards placed on the left side, and on the multitude of specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors on the right side of the said great Hall. After silence made among the people, The Act of Parliament, for the trying of <hi>CHARS STƲART</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> was read over by the Clerk of the Court, who sate on one side of the Table covered with a rich Turky Carpet, and placed at the feet of the said Lord President, upon which table was also laid the Sword and Mace.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36403:5"/>
            <p>After reading the said Act, the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral names of the Commissioners were called over, every one who wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, being eighty, as aforesaid, rising up, and answering to his call.</p>
            <p>Having again placed himself in his Chair, with his face towards the Court, silence being again ordered, the Lord President stood up and said.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHARLS STƲ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ART,</hi> King of <hi>England;</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England</hi> assembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being deeply sensible of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities that have been brought upon this Nation (which is f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xed upon you as the principall Author of it) have resolved to make inquisition for Blood, and according to that Debt and duty they owe to Justice, to God, the Kingdome, and themselves, and according to the Fundamental Power that rests in themselves, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to bring you to tryall and Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gment, and for that purpose have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36403:5"/> constituted this High Court of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, before which you are brought.</p>
               <p>This said, M. <hi>Cook</hi> Attorney for the Commonwealth (standing within a Bar on the right hand of the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) offered to speak, but the King having a staff in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand, held it up. and laid it upon the said M. <hi>Cooks</hi> shoulder two or three times, bidding him hold; nevertheless, the Lord President ordering him to go on, he said:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. <hi>Cook.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Lord, I am comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to charge <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> in the name of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England,</hi> with Treason and high Misdemeanors; I desire the said Charge may be read.</p>
               <p>The said Charge being deliverd to the Clerk of the Court, the Lord Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident ordered it should be read, but the King bid him hold: nevertheless, being commanded by the Lord Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to read it, the Clerk begun.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36403:6"/>
            <head>The Charge of the Commons of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland</hi> against <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> of high Treason, and other high crimes, exhibited to the High Court of Iustice.</head>
            <p>THat the said <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> being admitted King of <hi>England,</hi> and therein trus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with a <hi>limited Power,</hi> to govern by, and according to the Laws of the Land, and not otherwise; and by his Trust Oath, and Office, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obliged to use the power commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, <hi>for the good and benefit of the people,</hi> and for the preservation of their rights and liberties yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless out of a <hi>wicked design,</hi> to erect, and uphold in himself an unlimited and Tyrannicall power to rule <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Will,</hi> and to overthrow the Rights and Liberties of the people; yea, to take away, and make void the foundations, thereof and of all redress and remedy of misgovernment, which by the fundamentall Constitutions of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36403:6"/> this Kingdome, were reserve on the peoples behalf, in the right and power of frequent and successive parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or National meetings in Councel; he, the said <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> for accomplishment of such his <hi>designs</hi> and for protecting of himsef and his adherents, in his, and their <hi>wicked practises</hi> to the same Ends, hath tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terously and maliciously levyed War against the <hi>present Parliament, and the people therein represented</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Particularly, upon or about the thirtieth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thousand six hundred fourty and two at <hi>Beverley</hi> in the County of <hi>York,</hi> and upon or about the thirtieth day of <hi>July</hi> in the yeere aforesaid, in the County of the city of <hi>York,</hi> and upon or abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the twe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty fourth day of <hi>August,</hi> in the same yeare, at the County of the town of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> when, and where hee set up his <hi>Standard of Warr.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36403:7"/> And upon, or about the twenty third day of <hi>Octob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> in the same year, at <hi>Edge Hill</hi> and <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inton field,</hi> in the County of <hi>Warwick</hi> and upon, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the thirtieth day of <hi>November,</hi> in the same year, at <hi>Brainford,</hi> in the County of <hi>Middesex:</hi> and upon, or about the thirtieth day of <hi>August,</hi> in the year of our Lord, one thousand six hundred forty and three, at <hi>Cavesham Bridge,</hi> neer <hi>Reding,</hi> in the County of <hi>Berks:</hi> and upon, or about the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>October,</hi> in the year last mentioned, at, or neer the City of <hi>Glocester;</hi> and upon. or about the thirtieth day of <hi>November,</hi> in the year last mentioned, at <hi>Newberry,</hi> in the County of <hi>Berks,</hi> and upon, or about the one and thirtieth day of <hi>July,</hi> in the year of our Lord, one thousand six hundred forty and four, at <hi>Copredy-Bridge,</hi> in the County of <hi>Oxon:</hi> and upon, or about the thirtieth day of <hi>September,</hi> in the year last mentioned,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36403:7"/> at <hi>Bodmin,</hi> and other places neer adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, in the County of <hi>Cornwall;</hi> and upon, or about the thirtieth day of <hi>November,</hi> in the year last m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntioned, at <hi>Newbery</hi> aforesaid: and upon, or about the eighth day of <hi>Iune,</hi> in the year of our Lord, one thousand six hundred forty and five, at the town of <hi>Leicester:</hi> and also upon the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of the same month, in the same year, at <hi>Naseby field,</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Northampton,</hi> at which severall times and places, or most of them, and at many other places in this Land, at several other times, within the yeer afore mentioned: and in the year o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Lord, one thousand six hundred forty and six: he the said <hi>Charls Stuar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath caused and procured many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of the Free-People of the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be slain, and by <hi>Divisions, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Jnsurrections,</hi> within this land, by invasions from Forraign parts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured and procured by him, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36403:8"/> &amp; by <hi>many other evil ways &amp; means,</hi> he the said <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> hath not only <hi>maintained and carried on</hi> the said war, <hi>both by Land and Sea,</hi> during the years before mentioned; but also <hi>hath renewed, or caused to be renewed, the said War</hi> against the parliament, and good people of this Nation, in this present, one ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r thousand six hundred fourty and eight, in the County of <hi>Kent, Essex, Surrey, Sussex, Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex,</hi> and many other counties and places in England and Wales, and also by Sea: and particularly, he the said <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> hath for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, <hi>given Commission to his son,</hi> the Prince, and others; whereby, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es multitudes of other persons,</hi> many such as were by the parliament intrusted and imployed for the safety, of the Nation, being by him or his Agents corrupted, to the betraying of their trust, and revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the parliament, have had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36403:8"/> entertainment and commission, for the continuing and renewing of war and Hostility, against the said parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and people as aforesaid. By which cruell and unnaturall Wars by him the said <hi>CHARLS STV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ART,</hi> levyed, continued and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as aforesaid, much Innocent Blood of the Free-people of this nation hath been spilt: many Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies heve been undone, the publike treasury wasted and exhausted, Trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obstructed, and miserably decayed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vast expence and damage to the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rion incurred, and many parts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Land spoyled, some of them even to Desolation.</p>
            <p>And for further prosecution of his said evil Designs, he, the said <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> doth stil continue his commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions to the said prince, and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and Revolters, both English and Forreigners, and to the Earle of <hi>Ormand,</hi> and to the Irish Rebels, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36403:9"/>
               <hi>Revolters,</hi> associated with him: from whom further <hi>Jnvasions</hi> upon this Land are threatned, upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement, and on the behalf of the said <hi>Charls Stuart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which wicked <hi>Designs, VVars,</hi> and evil practises of him, the said <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> have been, and are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on, for the advancing and uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the pesonal interest of <hi>will and power,</hi> and pretended <hi>Prerogative</hi> to himself and his family, against the publique interest, Common Right, Liberty, Justice, and peace of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this nation, by, and for whom he was entrusted, as aforesaid:</p>
            <p>By all which it appeareth, that he, the said <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> hath been, and is the occasioner, Author, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver of the said unnaturall, cruell, and bloody Wars, and therein guilty of all the Treasons, Murthers, Rapines, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Spoils, Desolations, Damage, and mischief to this nation, acted or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36403:9"/> committed in the said Wars, or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned thereby.</p>
            <p>And the said <hi>John Cook,</hi> by protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion having on the behalf of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> the liberty of exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at any time hereafter any other Charge against the said <hi>Charls Stuart;</hi> and also of replying to the answers which the said <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> shall make to the premises, or any of them, or any other Charge that shall be so exhibited, doth for the said <hi>Treasons</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>Crimes,</hi> on the behalf of the said people of <hi>England,</hi> Impeach the said <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> as a Tyrant, Trayto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Murtherer, and a publike, and Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cable Enemy to the Commonwealt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>England.</hi> And pray, that the sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> may be put to answer all, and every the Premises, that such proceedings, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, tryals, sentence, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may be thereupon had, as shall be agreeable to Justice.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36403:10"/>
            <p>IT is observed, that the time the Charge was reading, the King sate down in his Chair, looking some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on the Court, somtimes up to the Galleries, and having risen again and turned about to behold the Guards, and spectators, sate down, ooking very sternly with a counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance not at all moved, til these words, <hi>viz. Charls Stuart</hi> to be a <hi>Tyrant</hi> and <hi>Traytor, &amp;c.</hi> were read, at which he laughed as he sate in the face of the Court.</p>
            <p>The charge being read the Lord president replyed:</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have now heard your charge read, containing such matters as appears in it; you find, that in the close of it, it is prayed to to the Court, in the behalf of the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that you answer to your Charge. The Court expects your answer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:36403:10"/>
               <speaker>The King:</speaker>
               <p>I would know by what power I am called hither; I was not long ago in the <hi>Jsle of Wight,</hi> how I came there, is a longer story than I think is fit at this time for me to speak of; but there I entred into a TREATY with both Houses of parliament with as much publique faith as it's possible to bee had of any people in the World: I trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there with a number of Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lords and Gentlemen, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted honestly and uprightly, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not say but they did very nobly with me, wee were upon a conclusion of the Treaty. Now I would know by what Authority, I mean lawful, there are many unlawful authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the world, Theeves and Robbers by the high way, but I would know by what authority I was brought f om thence, and carryed from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lace to place, and I know not what
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36403:11"/> and when <hi>I</hi> know by what lawful au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, I shall answer: Remember I am your king, and what sins you bring upon your heards, and the judgment of God upon this Land, think well upon it, I say, think wel upon it, before you go further from one sin in a greater; therefore let me know by what lawful authority I am seated here, and I shall not be unwilling to answer, in the mean time I shall not betray my trust, I have a trust com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to me by God, by old and lawfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> descent, I wil not betray it to answer to a new unlawfull authority, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore resolve me that, and you shall hear more of me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>If you had been pleased to have observed, what was hinted to you by the Court, at your first coming hither, you would have known by what authority; which authority requires you, in the name of the people of England, of which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36403:11"/> you are elected King, to answer them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>No Sir, <hi>I</hi> deny that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>If you acknowledg not the authority of the Court, they must procced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>I do tel them so, <hi>England</hi> was never an Elective Kingdome, but an hereditary Kingdom for neer these thousand years, therefore let me know by what authority I am called hither. I do stand more for the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my people than any here, that come to be my pretended Judges and therefore let me know, by what <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Authority</hi> I am seated here, and I will answer it, otherwise I will not answer it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, how really you have managed your Trust, is known: your way of answer is to interrogate the Court, which beseems not you in this condition. You have been told of it twice or thrice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Here is a Gentleman,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36403:12"/> Lievt. Col. <hi>Corbet,</hi> ask him if he did not bring me from the <hi>Isle of Wight</hi> by force? I do not come here as sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ing to the Court; I will stand as much for the priviledge of the house of Commons, rightly understood, as any man here whatsoever. I see no House of Lords here that may constitute a parliament, and the King too should have been. Is this the bringing of the King to his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament? Is this the bringing an end to the Treaty in the publike Faith of the World? Let me see a legall authority warrranted by the Word of God, the Scriptures, or warranted by the constitutions of the Kingdome, and I will An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have propounded a Question, and have been answered, seeing you will not answer, the Court will consider how to proceed, in the mean time,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36403:12"/> those that brought you hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are to take charge of you back again.</p>
               <p>The Court desires to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be all the answer you will give, or no.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I desire that you would give me, and all the World, satisfaction in this, let mee tell you, it is not a slight thing you are about I, am sworn to keepe the peace by that duty I owe to God and my Country, and I will do it to the last breath of my Body, and therefore you shall do well to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, first God, and then the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, by what Authority you do it, if you do it by a usurped Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that will not last long, There is a GOD in Heaven that will call you, and all that give you power, to account: Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie me in that, and I will An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, otherwise I betray my Trust,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36403:13"/> and the liberties of the people, and therefore think of that, and then I shall be willing. For I do avow, that it is as great a sin to withstand lawful authority, as it is to submit to a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall, or any other ways unlawful authority and therefore satisfie God, and me, and all the World in that, and you shall receive my answer; I am not afraid of the bill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>The Court expects you should give them a finall answer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir purpose is to adjourn till Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day next, if you do not satisfie your self, though we do tel you our author<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity; we are satisfied with our autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and it is upon <hi>Gods Authority</hi> and the Kingdoms, and that peace you speak of wil be kept in the doing of Justice, and that's our present work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Let me tel you, if you wil shew me what lawful authority you have, I shal be satisfied: but that you have said, satisfies no reasonable man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:36403:13"/>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>That's in your appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension: we think it reasonable that are your Judges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis not my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, nor yours neither, that ought to decide it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>The Court hath heard you, and you are to be disposed of as they have commanded. <hi>Two things were remarkable in this days pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is to be observed, that as the charge was reading against the King, the silver head of his staff fel off, the which he wondred at, and seeing none to take it up, he stooped for it himself.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That as the King was going away, he looked with a very austere coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance upon the Court, with stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his Hat replyed, wel Sir, when the <hi>Lord president</hi> commanded the Guard to take him away; and at his going down he said, <hi>J do not fear that,</hi> pointing with his staff at the sword.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36403:14"/> The people in the hall, as he went down the stairs cryed out, some, <hi>God save the King,</hi> and some for <hi>Justice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being called, the Court adjourned til Monday next, <hi>Ianuary</hi> 22. at 9. in the morning to the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chamber, and from thence to the same place again in <hi>Wistminster</hi> Hall.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>At the high Court of Iustice sitting in VVestminster Hall, Monday, Ianuary <hi>22. 1648.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Yes made: Silence commanded. The Court called, and answered to their names.</p>
            <p>Silence commanded upon pain of imprisonment, and the Captain of the Guard to apprehend all such as make disturbance.</p>
            <p>Upon the Kings comming in, a shout was made,</p>
            <p>Command given by the Court to the Captain of the Guard to fetch and take into his custody, those who make any disturbance.</p>
            <sp>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36403:14"/>
               <speaker>Mr. Sollicitor.</speaker>
               <p>May it please your Lordship, my Lord President.</p>
               <p>I did at the last Court in the behalf of the Commons of England, exhibit and give into this Court a Charge of High Treason, and other high Crimes, against the prisoner at the Bar, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I do accuse him in the name of the people of England, and the Charge was read unto him, and his answer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. My Lord, hee was not then pleased to give an Answer, but instead of answering, did there dispute the Authority of this high Court. My humble motion to this high <hi>Court,</hi> in behalf of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> is, That the prisoner may be directed to make a positive Answer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i her by way of <hi>Consession</hi> or <hi>Negation;</hi> which if he shall refuse to do, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Charge</hi> may be taken <hi>pro con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesso,</hi> and the <hi>Court</hi> may proceed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to justice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36403:15"/>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member at the last Court you were told the occasion of your being brought hither, and you heard a Charge against you, containing a Charge of High Treason, and other▪ high Crimes, against this Realm of England: you heard likewise, that it was prayed in the behalf of the people that you should give an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to that Charge, that thereupon such proceedings might be had as should be agreeable to justice; you were then pleased to make some scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples concerning the Authority of this Court, and knew not by what authority you were brought hither; you did divers times propound your questions, and were as often answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That it was by authority of the <hi>Commons of England assembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> that did think fit to call you to account for those high and capita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> misdemeanours wherewith you were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36403:15"/> then charged: Since that, the Court hath taken into consideration what you then said, they are fully satisfied with their own authority, and they hold it fit you should stand satisfied with it too: and they do require it, that you do give a positive and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular answer to this Charge that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited against you, they do expect you should either confess or deny it, if you deny, it is offered in the behalf of the Kingdome to be made go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> against you, their authority they do avow to the whole World, that the whole Kingdome are to rest satisfied in, and you are to rest satisfied with it, and therefore you are to lose no more time, but to give a positive Answer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King,</speaker>
               <p>When I was here last, 'tis true, I made that question, and truly if it were only my own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar case, I would have satisfyed my self
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36403:16"/> with the protestation I made the last time I was here against the lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this Court, and that a King cannot be tryed by any Superior Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction on Earth; but it is not my case alone, it is the Freedom and the liberty of the people of <hi>England,</hi> and do you pretend what you wil, I stand more for their liberties, for if power without law may make laws, may alter the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>damental laws of the kingdom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> know what Subject he is in <hi>England,</hi> that can be sure of his life, or any thing that he calls his own; therfore when that I came here, I did expect particular Reasons, to know by what law, what authority you did, proceed against me here, and therefore I am a little to seek what to say to you in this particular, because the affirmative is to be proved, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative often is very hard to doe; but since I cannot perswade you to do it, I shall tel you my reasons as short as I can.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36403:16"/>
               <p>My reasons why in conscience, and the duty I owe to God, first and my people next, for the preservation of their lives, liberties, and estates, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive I cannot answer this, till I be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of the legality of it.</p>
               <p>All proceedings against any man whatsoever—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>L. pr.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I must interrupt you, which I would not do, but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a what you do is not agreeable to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any Court of Justice, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re about to enter into argument, and dispute concerning the authority of this Court, before whom you appear as a Prisoner, and are charged as an high Delinquent, if you take upon you to dispute the authority of the Court, we may not do it, nor will any Court give way unto it, you are to submit unto it, you are to give in a punctal and direct answer, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will answer your Charge or no, and what your answer is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36403:17"/>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, by your favor, I do not know the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rms of Law, I do know Law and Reason, though I am no Lawyer professed, but I know as much Law as any Gentleman in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland: and therefore under favour, I do plead for the Liberties of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of England more than you do, and therefore if I should impose a beliefe upon any man without reasons given for it, it were unreasonable; but <hi>I</hi> must tel you, that that reason that <hi>I</hi> have as thus formed, I cannot yeild unto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I must interrupt you, you may not be permitted, you speak of Law and Reason, it is fit there should be Law and Reason and there is both against you. Sir, the Vote of the Commons of England as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled in Parliament, it is the reason of the Kingdom, and they are these too that have given that Law, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which you should have ruled and raigned: Sir, you are not to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36403:17"/> our authority; you are told it again by the Court, Sir, it wil be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, that you stand in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Court, and your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt wil be recorded accordingly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>I do not know how a King can be a Delinquent, not by any Law that ever I heard of, all men, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, or what you wil, let me tel you, they may put in Demurrer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any proceeding as legal, and I do demand that, and demand to be heard with my reasons, if you deny that, you deny reason.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have offered somthing to the Court, I shall speak something unto you the sense of the Court. Sir, neither you nor any man are to dispute that point, you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, you may not demur the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction of the Court, if you do, I must let you know, that they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule your Demurrer, they sit here by the authority of the Commons of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36403:18"/>
                  <hi>England,</hi> and all your predecessors, and you are responsible to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>I deny that, shew me one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you ought not to interrupt while the Court is speaking to you, this point is not to be debated by you, neither will the Court permit you to do it, if you offer it by way of Demurrer to the Jurisdiction of the Court, they have consider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of their Jurisdiction, they do affirm their own Jurisdiction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>I say Sir, by your favor, that the commons of <hi>England</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a court of Judicature, I would know how they came to be so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you are not to be permitted to go on in that speech, and these discours<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</p>
               <p>Then the Clerk of the Court read, as followeth.</p>
               <p>Charls Stuart <hi>King of England, you have been accused on the behalf of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36403:18"/> people of England, of high Treason, and other high Crimes, the Court have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined that you ought to answer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> same.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> will answer the same so soon as I know by what authority you do this:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>If this be all that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will say, then, Gentlemen, you tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought the Prisoner hither, take charge of him back again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>I do require that I ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> give in my reasons why <hi>J</hi> do not an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swer, and give me time for that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, tis not for priso<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners to require.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Prisone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s? sir, <hi>J</hi> am no an ordinary prisoner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>The court hath co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of their jurisdiction, and the have already affirmed their jurisdict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on; if you wil not answer, we sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> give order to record your default.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>You never heard my re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:36403:19"/>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, your Reasons are not to be heard against the highest Jurisdiction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King:</speaker>
               <p>Shew me that Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on where reason is not be heard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, we shew it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou here, the Commons of <hi>England;</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the next time you are brought, you will know more of the pleasure of the Court, and, it may be, their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all determination.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Shew me where ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he House of Commons was a Court <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Judicature of that kind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Serjeant, take away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Prisoner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Wel sir, remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the King is not suffered to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Reasons for the Libertie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reedome of all his subjects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o have Liberty to use this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age; how great a friend you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en to the Law and liberties of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36403:19"/> people, let all <hi>England</hi> and the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> judg.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Sir under favour, it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Liberty, Freedome, and La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Subject that ever I too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> —defended my self with Arms never took up Arms against the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, but for the Laws.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>The command <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the court must be obeyed; no an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wer will be given to the charge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Wel sir.</p>
               <p>Then the Lord President ordere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the default to be recorded, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contempt of the Court and that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> answer would be given to the charge</p>
               <p>And so was guarded forth to Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bert Cottons</hi> house.</p>
               <p>Then the Court adjourned to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> painted Chamber on Tuesday a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> twelve a clock, and from thence the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intend to adjourn to <hi>Westminster</hi> Hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at which time all persons concerne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are to give their attendance;</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:36403:20"/>
            <head>At the high Court of Justice sitting in <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> Tuesday Jan. <hi>23. 1648.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Yes made, Silence commanded.</p>
            <p>The Court called, Seventy three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ersons present.</p>
            <p>The King comes in with his Guard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooks with an austere countenance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the Court; and sits down.</p>
            <p>The second O Yes made, and silence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommanded.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Cook</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Solicitor General, may it please your Lordshiy, my Lord Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
               <p>This is now the third time, that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he great grace and favour of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh Court, the prisoner hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rought to the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r before any issue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyned in the cause. My Lord, I did at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he first Court exhibite a Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainst him, containing the highest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reason that ever was wrought upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Theatre</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> that a King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f <hi>England,</hi> trusted to keep the Law,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36403:20"/> that had taken an oath so to do, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had tribute paid him for that en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> should be guilty of a wicked desig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> subvert and destroy our Laws, and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>troduce an <hi>Arbitrary, and Tycannica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Government,</hi> in the defence of the <hi>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liament and their authority,</hi> set up h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Standard for War against his Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and people, and I did humbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pray, in the behalf of the <hi>people of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland,</hi> that he might speedily be requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to make answer to the Charge.</p>
               <p>But my Lord, instead of makin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny answer, he did then dispute t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> authority of this High Court, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lordship was pleased to give him further day to consider and to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his answer, which day bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yesterday, I did humbly move, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he might be required to give a dire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and positive answer, either by d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nying or confession of it, but n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, hee was then pleasad for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> demur to the jurisdiction of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36403:21"/> Court, which the Court did then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er-rule, and command him to give a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rect and positive answer. My Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esides this great delay of Iustice, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al now humbly move your Lordship <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or speedy judgment against him: My <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord, I might press your Lordship up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the whole, that according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nown Rules of the Law of the Land, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at if a prisoner shall stand as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>macious in contempt, and shall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at in an issuable plea, guilty, or not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uilty of the Charge given against <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, whereby he may come to a faire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryal; that as by an implicite confesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n it may be taken <hi>pro confesso,</hi> as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th been done to those who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>served more favor than the prisoner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Bar hath done: But besides, my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd, I shall humbly press your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip upon the whole Fact; the House <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Commons, the supreme authority <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d jurisdiction of the Kingdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey have declared; That it is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36403:21"/> that the matter of the Charge is true, as it is in truth, my Lord, as clear as Chrystal, and as the Sun that shines at noon day, which if your Lordship and the Court be not satisfied in, I have notwithstanding, on the people of Englands behalf, several witnesses to produce: And therefore I do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray, (and yet I must confess, it is not so much I, as the innocent blood that hath been shed, the cry whereof is very great for justice and judgment) that speedy judgment be pronounced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainst the prisoner at the bar.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, You have heard what is moved by the Council on the behalf of the Kingdome against you, sir, you may well remember, and if you do not, the Court cannot forget what delatory dealings the court hath found at your hands, you were pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to propound some Questions, you have had your resolution upon them You were told over and over againe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36403:22"/> That the Court did affirm their own Jurisdiction: that it was not for you nor any man, to dispute the <hi>Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the supream and highest authority of England,</hi> from which there is no appeal, and touching which there must be no dispute; yet you did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in such carriage, as you gave no manner of obedience, nor did you acknowledg any authority in them, nor the high Court, that constituted this Court of Justice.</p>
               <p>Sir, I must let you know from the Court, that they are very sensible of these delays of yours, and that they ought not, being thus authorized by the supream Court of England, to be thus trifled withall, and that they might in justice, if they pleased, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccording to the rules of justice, take advantage of these delays, and proceed to pronounce judgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainst you; yet nevertheless they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re pleased to give direction, and on
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36403:22"/> their behalf, I do require you, that you make a positive answer unto the charge that is against you, sir, in plain terms, for Justice knows no respect of persons: you are to give your posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and finall answer in plain English, whether you be guilty or not guilty of these Treasons laid to your charge.</p>
               <p>The King after a little pause, said, When I was here yesterday, I did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to speak for the Liberties of the people of England; I was interrupted: I desire to know yet whether I may speak freely or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>L. Pr.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have heard the resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the court upon the like questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the last day, and you were told, that having such a Charge of so high a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture against you, and your work was, that you ought to acknowledg the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction of the court, <hi>and to answer to your</hi> Charge. Sir, if you answer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o your Charge, which the court gives you leave now to do, though they might
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36403:23"/> have taken the advantage of your contempt, yet if you be able to answer to your Charge, when you have once answered, you shall be heard at large, make the best defence you can: But Sir, I must let you know from the Court, as their commands, that you are not to be permitted to issue out into any other discourses, till such time as you have given a positive answer concerning the matter that is charged upon you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King</speaker>
               <p>For the Charge, I value it not a R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sh, it is the Liberty of the people of England that I stand for, for me to acknowledg a new Court that I never heard of before, I that am your King, that should be an example to all the people of England for to uphold Justice, to maintain the old Laws; indeed I do not know how to do it, you spoke very well the first day that I came here, on Saturday of the Obligations that I had laid upon me
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36403:23"/> by God, to the maintenance of the Liberties of my people: The same Obligation you speak of, I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg to God, that I owe to him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my people, to defend as much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e lies, the ancient Laws of the Kingdom, therefore until that I may know that this is not against the <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws</hi> of the kingdom, by your favour I can put in no particular<note n="*" place="margin">This is as the King ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>press'd.</note> Charge; if you will give me time, I will shew you my reasons why, but <hi>J suposed —</hi> I cannot do it, and this —<hi>he means ans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here being interrupted he said By your favor, you ought not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>upt me, how I came here I know not, there's no Law for it, to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our King your Prisoner: <hi>J</hi> was in a Treaty upon the publique faith of the Kingdome, that was the known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> two Houses at Parliament that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36403:24"/> was the representive of the Kingdom, and when that I had almost made an end of the Treaty, then I was hurried away, and brought hither and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore —</p>
               <p>Here the Lord president said, Sir, you must know the pleasure of the Court.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>by your favor Sir,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Nay Sir, by your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, you may not be permitted to fal into those discourses, you appear as a Delinquent, you have not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>horitie of the Court, the Court craves it not of you, but once more t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey command you, to give your positive answer—<hi>Clerk</hi> do your duty</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King</speaker>
               <p>Duty Sir!</p>
               <stage>The Clerk reads</stage>
               <p>Charls Stuart King of England, <hi>You are accused in the behalf of the commons of England, of divers high crimes and treasons, which charge hath been read unto you; the Court now requires you to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36403:24"/> give your positive and finall answer, by way of confession or denial of the charge.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I say again to you, so that I might give satisfaction to the people of England of the clearness of my proceeding, not by way of answer, nor in this way, but to satisfie them that I have done nothing against that trust that hath been committed to me, I would do it; but to ackowledg a new Court against their priviledges, to alter the fundamental Laws of the Kingdome, Sir, you must excuse me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, this is the third time that you have publiquely disow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this Court, and put an affront up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; how far you have preserved priviledges of the people, your actions have spoke it, but truly Sir, mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions ought to be known by their actions, you have written your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in bloody Characters through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Kingdome, but Sir, you understand the pleasure of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36403:25"/> court — Clerk Record the default— and Gentlemen you that took charge of the prisoner, take him back again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>I wil onely say this one word more to you, if it were onely My own particular, I would not say any more nor interrupt you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord Pres.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have heard the pleasure of the Court, and you are (notwithstanding you will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it] to finde that you are before a Court of Justice.</p>
               <p>Then the King went forth with his Guard, and proclamation was made, that all persons who had then appeard and had further to doe at the Court, might depart into the Painted Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to which place the Court did forthwith adjourn, and intended to meet in <hi>Westminster Hall</hi> by ten of the clock the next morning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cryer.</speaker>
               <p>God bless the Kingdom of England.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:36403:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Wednesday,</hi> January 24 1648.</head>
            <p>THis day it was expected the high Court of Iustice should have met in <hi>VVestminster</hi> Hall about ten of the clock, but at the time appointed, one of the Vshers by direction of the Court, then sitting in the <hi>Painted Chamber,</hi> gave notice to the people there assembled, that in regard the court was then upon the examination of Witnesses in relation to present af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, in the <hi>painted Chamber,</hi> they could not sit there: but all persons ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be there, were to appear upon further summons.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The proceedings of the High Court of Justice sitting in <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> on Saturday the <hi>27.</hi> of Ianuary, <hi>1648.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Yes made; Silence commanded. The Court called, Serjeant <hi>Bradshaw,</hi> Lord president in a Scarlet to be, with 68. other Members of the Court.</p>
            <p>As the King comes in, a cry made
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36403:26"/> in the Hall for execution justice, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>I shall desire a word to be heard a little, and <hi>I</hi> hope I shal give no occasion of interruption.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>You may answer in your time, hear the Court first.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Jf it please you, Sir, I desire to be heard, and I shall not give any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion or interruption, and it is only in a word, a sudden judgment—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you shall be heard in due time, but you are to hear the Court first.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I desire it, it wil be in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to what I believe the Court will say, and therefore sir, a hasty judgment is not so soon recalled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you shall be heard before the judgment be given, and in the meantime you may forbeare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Wel Sir, sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l I be heard hefore the judgment be given.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:36403:26"/>
               <speaker>Lord pres.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, it is well known to all, or most of you here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, that the prisoner at the bar hath been severall times convented and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rought before the Court to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nswer to a Charge of Treason, and other high Crimes exhibited against him in the name of the people of<note n="*" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> e a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> saying, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot half the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; b t sh e was so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> England; to which Charge being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to Answer, Hee hath been so farre from obeying the Commands of the Court by submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their Iustice, as Hee began to take upon him to offer reasoning and debate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Authority of the Court, and of the highest court that constituted them to try and judg him; but being overru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in that, &amp; req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ired co make his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, he was still pleased to continue contumacious, &amp; to refuse to submit or answer: Hereupon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e court that they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36403:27"/> may not be waning to themselves, to the trust reposed in them, nor that any mans wilfulness prevent ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, they have thought fit to take the matter into their consideration: they have considered of the contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and of that confession, which in Law doth arise pon that contumacy; they have likewise considered of the notoriety of the Fact charged upon this Prisoner, and upon the whole matter they are resolved, and have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon a sentence to be now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced against this Prisoner; but in respect he doth desire to be heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the sentence be read, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, the Court hath resolved that they wil hear him; yet Sir, thus much I must tel you before-hand, which you have been minded of at other Courts; that if that you have to say be to off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r any d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bate concerning jurisd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction, you are not to be heard in it, you have offered it formerly, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36403:27"/> you have indeed struck at the root, that is the power and <hi>supream authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Commons of England,</hi> which this Court will not admit a debate of, and which indeed is an irrationall thing in them to do, being a Court that acts upon Authority derived from them, that they should presume to judg upon their superiority, from whom there, no Appeal: But Sir, if you have any thing to say in defence of your self concerning the matters charged, the Court hath given me command to let you know they will hear you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King.</speaker>
               <p>Since that I see that you wil not hear any thing of debate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that which I confess I thought most material for the peace of the Kingdom, and for the Liberty of the Subject, I shall wave it, <hi>J</hi> shall speak nothing to it; but onely I must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you, that this many a day all things have been taken away from me, but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36403:28"/> that that I call more deare to mee then my Life, which is, <hi>My Conscience and my Honour;</hi> and if I had respect to my life more than the peace of the Kingdome, the Libertie of the Subject, certainlie I should have made a particular defence for my selfe, for by that at least-wise I might have delayed an uglie sentence, which <hi>J</hi> believe wil pass upon me: therefore certainlie sir, as a man that hath some understanding, so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e knowledge of the world, if that my true zeale to my Countrie had not over born the care that I have of my own preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I should have gone another way to work than that I have done: now Sir I conceive, that an hastie sentence once past, may be sooner repented then recalled, and trulie, the self same desire that I have for <hi>the peace of the kingdome, and the Liberty of the subiect more than my own particular,</hi> does make me now at last desire, that having som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:36403:28"/> for to say that concerns both, I desire before sentence be given, that I may be heard in the Painted Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber before the Lords and Commons, this delay cannot be prej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicial to you whatsoever I say, if <hi>I</hi> say no reason, those that heare me must be Judges, I cannot be Judg of that that <hi>J</hi> have, if it be reason, and reallie for the welfare of the Kingdom, and the libertie of the Subject, J am sure on't verie well 'tis worth the hearing; therefore I do conjure you, as you love that you pretend, J hope it's reall the libertie of the subject, the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that you wil grant me the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring before any sentence be passed, J onlie desire this, that you wil take this into your consideration, it may be you have not heard of it before hand, if you wil i'le retire, &amp; you may think of it, but if I cannot get this libertie, I do here protest that so fair shews of <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> and Peace are pure shews, and not otherwise then that You will
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36403:29"/> not hear your KING:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have now spoker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Yes Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord Pres.</speaker>
               <p>And this that you have said is a further declining of the <hi>ju is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of this Court,</hi> which was the thing wherein you were limited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Pray excuse me Sir, for my interruption, because you mistake me, it is not a declining of it, you do judg me before you hear me speak, I say it wil not, <hi>I</hi> do not decline it, though I cannot acknowledg the jurisdiction of the Court: yet sir, in this give me leave to say, <hi>I</hi> would do it, though I did not acknowledg it in this, I do protest it is not the declining of it, since I say, if that I do say any thing but that, that is for the Peace of the Kingdom and the Libertie of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, then the shame is mine. Now I desire, that you will take this into your
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36403:29"/> consideration, if you wil Ile withdraw.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, this it not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether new that you have moved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, not altogether new to us, though the first time in person you have offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to the Court, Sir, you say you do not decline the jurisdiction of the Court▪</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Not in this that I have said▪</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord President.</speaker>
               <p>I understand you wel Sir, but nevertheless that which you have offered, seems to be contrary to that saying of yours; for the Court are ready to give a sentence: it is not as you say, that they will not hear your King, for they have been ready to hear you, they have patiently wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your pleasure for three Courts together to hear what you would say to the peoples Charge against you▪ to which you have not vouchsafed to give any answer at all: sir, this tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to a further delay: truly sir, such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays as these, neither may the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:36403:30"/> nor Justice wel bear; you have had three several daies to have offered in this kind what you would have pleased; This Court is founded upon that Authoritie of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England, in whom rests the supreme jurisdiction, that which you now tender is to have another juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and a <hi>coordinate Jurisdiction:</hi> I know verie wel you express your self, Sir, that notwithstanding that you would offer to the Lords and Commons in the Painted Chamber, yet nevertheless you would proceed on here, I did hear you say so, but sir, that you would offer there, whatever it is must needs be in delay, of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce here; so as if this Court be resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and prepared for the sentence, this that you offer they are not bound in justice to grant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but sir, according to that you se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m to desire, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause you shall know the further pleasu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Court upon that which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36403:30"/> you have moved, the Court will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw for a time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Shall I with draw?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord pres.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you shall know the pleasure of the Court presently. The Court withdraws for half an hour into the <hi>Court of Wards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Serjeant at Arms, the Court give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> command that the prisoner be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, and they give order for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> return again.</p>
               <p>The Court withdraws for half an hour and returns:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord pres.</speaker>
               <p>Serjeant at Arms send fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your prisoner.</p>
               <p>Sir, you were pleased to make a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion here to the Court, to offer a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of yours touching the propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of somwhat to the Lords in the painted Chamber for the peace o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Kingdom, sir, you did in eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> receiue an answer before the Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> adjourned: Truly Sir, their with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing and adjournment was <hi>pro for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matantum,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:36403:31"/> for it did not seem to them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat there was any difficultie in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing, they have considered of what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou have moved, and have considered of their own Authoritie, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounded, as hath been often said, upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he supream authoritie of the Commons of England assembled in Parliament. The Court acts according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to their commission, sir, the return <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have to you from the Court, is this, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat they have been too much delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you already, and this that you now offer hath occasioned some little further delay, and they are Judges ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the highest Judges, and Judges are no more to delay, then they are to denie justice, they are good words in the old. <hi>Charter of England: Nulli negabimus, nulli vendemus, nulli deferemus Iustitiam,</hi> There must be no delay, but the truth is sir, and so every man here observes it, that you have much delayed them in your contempt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36403:31"/> and default, for which they migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> long since have proceeded to judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment against you, and notwithstandin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what you have offered, they are r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>solved to proceed to punishment, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to judgment, and that is their unan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mous resolution.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I know it is in vain so me to dispute, I am no <hi>Sceptick</hi> for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> denie the power that you have, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know that you have power enough Sir, I confess, I think it would ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been for the kingdoms Peace, if yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would have taken the pains for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have shown the lawfulness of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power, for this delay that I have des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, I confess it is a delay, but it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> delay verie important for the peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Kingdom, for it is not my perso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that I look on alone, it is the kingdo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> welfare, and the kingdoms peace, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an old sentence, <hi>That we should this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> on long before we have resolved of gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> matters suddenly:</hi> therefore sir, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:36403:32"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y again, that I do put at your doors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l the inconveniency of an hasty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entence, I confesse <hi>J</hi> haue been here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow I think this week, this day eight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys was the day I came here first. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t a little delay of a day or two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rther may giue peace, whereas an <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>asty judgment</hi> may bring on that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouble and <hi>perpetual inconveniency</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Kingdome, that the child that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unborn may repent it; and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain, out of the duty <hi>I</hi> owe to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to my Countrey, I do desire that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be heard by the Lords and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommons in the painted Chamber, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any other that you will appoint me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord pre.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you have been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> answered to what you even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w moved being the same you mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d before, since the resolution and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> judgment of the Court in it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Court now requires to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow whether you have any more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> say for your self, then you haue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36403:32"/> said, before they proceed to Sentence:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>I say this, sir, That if you wil hear me, if you wil giue me but this delay, I doubt not but I shall giue some satisfaction to you all here, and to my people after that, and therefore I do require you, as you wil answer it at the dreadfull day of Judgment, that you wil consider it once again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord pres.</speaker>
               <p>Sir I haue receiued direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Court.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Wel sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>L p.</speaker>
               <p>If this must be reenforced or any thing of this natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, your answer must be the same, and they will proceed to sentence, if you haue no more to say.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>I haue nothing more to say, but I shall desire that this may be entred what I haue said.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>L. p.</speaker>
               <p>The Court then sir hath som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to say unto you, which although I know it will be uerie unacceptable, yet notwithstanding, they are willing &amp; are resolued to discharge their duty</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:36403:33"/>
               <p>Sir, you speak very wel of a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing that you call peace, and it had been much to be wished that God had put it into your heart, that you had as effectualy and really endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and studied the peace of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as now in words you seem to pretend, but as you were told the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, Actions must expound inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet actions have been clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and truly, Sir, it doth appear plainly enough to them, that you have gone upon very erronious principles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he kingdom hath felt it to their smart, and it wil be no ease to you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hink of it, for Sir, you have held your self, and let fall such language, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f you had been no ways subject to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Law, or that the Law had not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>een your superior. Sir the Court is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery wel sensible of it, and I hope so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re all the understanding people of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngland, that the Law is your supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or, that you ought to have ruled ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36403:33"/> to the Law, you ought to have done so Sir, <hi>J</hi> know very well your pretence hath been that you have done so, but Sir, the difference hath been who shall be the <hi>Expositors of this Law;</hi> Sir, whether you and your party out of Courts of Justice shall take upon them to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound Law, or the Courts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Justice, who are the expounders; nay, the Soveraign and the High Court of Justice, the parliament of England, who are not only <hi>the highest expounders,</hi> but <hi>the sole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>akers of the Law.</hi> Sir, for you to set your self with your single judgment, and those that adhere unto you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Highest Court of Justice, that is not Law Sir, as the Law is your superior, so truly sir, there is somthing that is superior to the Law, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is indeed the <hi>Parent or Author</hi> of the law, and that is the people of England▪ for Sir, as they are those that at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> first, as other Countries have done
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:36403:34"/> did chose to themselves this form of Government, even for justice sake, that justice might be administred, that peace might be preserved; so sir, they gave Laws to their Governors, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which they should govern; &amp; if those Laws should have proued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenient, or prejudiciall to the publique, they had a power in them, and reserved to themselves to alter as they shall see cause; sir, it is very true, what some of your side have said, <hi>Rex non habet parem in Regno;</hi> This Court wil say the same, while <hi>King, that you have not your Peer</hi> in some sense, for you are <hi>Major singulis,</hi> but they will aver again, that you are <hi>Minor univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis,</hi> and the same Author tels you that <hi>in exhibitione juris,</hi> there you have no power, but in
<q>quasi mivimus.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This we know to be Law,</hi> Rex habet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uperiorem, Deum &amp; Legem, etiam &amp; curiam, <hi>and so saies the same
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:36403:34"/> Author, and truly Sir, he makes bol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to go a little further,</hi> Debentei ponere frenum, <hi>They ought to bridle him, and sir, we know very wel the stories ef old; Those, Wars that waye called Barons Wars, when the Nobility of the Land did stand out for the Liberty and property of the subiect, and would not suffer the Kings that did invade to play the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants freer, but called them to account for it, we know that truth, that they did</hi> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enum ponere, <hi>but sir, if they do forbear to do their duty now and are not so mindful of their own Honor and the Kingdoms good, as the Barons of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland will not be unmindfull of what is for their preservation, and for their safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Justitia fruendi, causa Reges consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti sunt! <hi>This we learn the end of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Kings or any other Governors it's for the enjoying of Iustice, that's the end. Now Sir, if so be the King will goe contrary to the end of his GOVERNMENT Sir, hee
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:36403:35"/> must understand that he is but an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of trust, and he ought to discharge that trust, and they are to take order for the animadversion and punishment of such an offending Governor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is not Law of yesterday sir, since the time of the division betwixt you and your people, but it is Law of old; and we know very well the Authors and the Authorities that do tel us what the Law was in that point upon the election of Kings, upon the Oath that they took unto their people, and if they did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve it, there were those things called Parliaments; the Parliaments were they that were to adjudg, the very words of the Author,</hi> the plaints and wrongs done of the King and the Queen, or their Children, such wrong especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie when the people could have no where else any remedie. <hi>Sir, that hath been the people of Englands case, they could not have their remedy else where but in Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:36403:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, Parliaments were ordained for that purpose to redress the grievances of the people, that was their main end; and truly sir, if so be that the Kings of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland had been rightly mindfull of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, they were never more in Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty and state then in the parliament: but how forgetful some have been, stories have told us; we have a miserable, a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, a sad experience of it, sir, by the old Laws of England, J speak these things the rather to you because you were pleased to let fall the other day you thought you had as much knowledg in the Law, as most Gentlemen in England, it is very wel sir. And truly Sir, it is very good for the Gentlemen of England to understand that Law under which they must live, and by which they must be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>verned, and then Sir, the Scriptures says,</hi> They that know their Master wil and do it not, <hi>what follows, the Law is your Master, the acts of parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:36403:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The parliaments were to be kept anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently we find in our Author twice in the year, that the subject upon any occasion might have a ready remedy and redress for his grievance. Afterwards by several acts of parliament in the days of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessor</hi> Edw. <hi>the</hi> 3 <hi>they must have been once a year.</hi> Sir, what intermission of Parliaments hath been in your time it is very wel known, and the sad conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it, and what in the interim instead of these Parliaments, hath been by you by an high and arbitrary hand introduced upon the people, that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise hath been too wel known &amp; felt, but when God by his providence had so brought it about, that you could no longer decline the calling of a parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, sir yet it wil appear what your ends were aginst the ancient and your native kingdome of Scotland: the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England not serving your ends against them, you were pleased to dissolve it. Another great necessity oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36403:36"/> the calling of this parliament, and what your designs &amp; plots &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours all along have been for the ruining &amp; confounding of this parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath been very notorious to the whole kingdom; &amp; truly sir, in that you did strike at all, that had been a sure way to have brought about that that this lays upon you, your intentions to subvert the fundamental laws of the land. For the great bulwark of libertie of the people, is the parliament of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and to subvert and root up that w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> your aim hath bin to do, certainly at one blow you had confounded the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and the property of England. Truly sit, it makes me call to mind, I cannot forbeare to express it, for sir. we must deal plainly with you, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the merits of your cause, so is our Commission, it makes me call to mind (these proceedings of yours) that we raad of a great <hi>Roman Emperor,</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he way let us cal him <hi>a great Roman</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:36403:37"/> Caligula, that wisht that the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had had but one neck, that at one blow he might cut it off. <hi>and your proceedings hath been somwhat like to this, for the body of the people of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland hath been, and where else repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented but in the parliament, and could you have but confounded that, you had at one blow cut off the neck of England, but God hath reserved better things for us, and hath pleased for to confound your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, and to break your Forces, and to bring your person into Custody that you might be responsible to Justice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, we know very wel that it is a question on your side very much prest, by what president we shall proceed? Truly sir, for presidents, J shall not upon these occasions institute any long discourse but it is no new thing to cite presidents al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of all Nations, where the people when power hath been in their hands, have been made bold to call their Kings to account, and where the change of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36403:37"/> hath upon occasion of the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anny and mis-Government of those that have been placed over them, J wil not spend time to mention</hi> France <hi>or</hi> Spain, <hi>or the Empire, or other countries, volumes may be written of them, but truly sir, that of the Kingdom of Arragon,</hi> I <hi>shall think some of us have thought upon it, when they have the justice of Arragon, that is a man</hi> tanquam in medio positus, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the King of Spain &amp; the people of the Countrey, that if wrong be done by the King he that is the King of Arragon, the Justice hath power to reform the wrong and he is acknowledged to be the Kings superior, and is the grand preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of their priviledges, and hath prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted Kings upon their miscarriages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir what the Tribunes of</hi> Rome <hi>were heretofore, and what the</hi> Ephori <hi>were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the</hi> Lacedemonian State, <hi>we know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat is the parliament of England to the English State, and though</hi> Rome <hi>seem to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave lost its Liberty, when once the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36403:38"/> Emperors were, yet you shall finde some famous Acts of Justice even done by the</hi> Senate of Rome, <hi>that great Tyrant of his time.</hi> Nero, <hi>condemned and iudged by the</hi> Senate.</p>
               <p>But truly Sir, to you I should not mention these Forraign examples and stories. If you look but over <hi>Tweed,</hi> we finde enough in your native kingdom of Scotland. If we look to your first King <hi>Fergustus,</hi> that your stories make mention of, he was an elective King, he dyed, and left two Sons both in their minority, the Kingdome made choice of their Unkle his Brother to govern in the minority, afterwards the elder Brother giving small hopes to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that he would rule or govern wel, seeking to supplant that good Unkle of his that Gouerned then justly, they set the elder aside, and took to the younger, sir, if J should come to what your stories make mention of, you know uery well you are the 109, King
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36403:38"/> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for to mention so many Kings as that Kingdome accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding co their power and priviledges have made bold to deal withall, some to banish, and some to imprison, and some put to death, it would be too long; and as one of your Authors says, it would be too long to recite the manifold examples that your own stories make mention of, <hi>Reges</hi> say they, we do create, we created Kings at first, <hi>Leges, &amp;c.</hi> We im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sed Laws upon them, and as they are chosen by the suffrages of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at the first, so upon just occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the same suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ages, they may be taken down again: and we will be bold to say, that no Kingdome hath yeilded more plentifull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then that your Native King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath done concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that deposition, and the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their offending and transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:36403:39"/>
               <p>It is not far to go for an example neer you, your Grandmother set aside and your Father an Infant crowned, and the State did it here in England, here hath not been a want of some examples, they have made bold, the Parliament and people of England, to call their Kings to account, here are frequent examples of it in the Saxons times, the time before the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, since the Conquest there wants not some Presidents neither, King <hi>Ed.</hi> the 2. K. <hi>Richard</hi> 2. they were dealt with so by the parliament, as they were deposed and deprived: and truly sir, who ever shal look into their stories, they shall not finde the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles that are charged upon them to come neer to that height and capital<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Crimes that are laid to your charge, nothing neer.</p>
               <p>Sir, you were pleased to say the other day, wherein they discent, and I did not contradict it, but take alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36403:39"/> Sir, if you were as the charge speaks, and no otherwise admitted King of England, but for that you were pleased then to alledg, how that almost for a thousand yeeres these things have been, stories wil tell you, if you goe no higher then the time of the Conquest, if you do come down since the Conquest, you are the 24th. King, from <hi>William</hi> called the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, you shal find one half of them to come meerly from the State, and not meerly upon the point of descent, it were easie to be instanced to you, the time must not be lost that way. And truly Sir, what a grave and learned Judge in his time, and wel known to you, and is since printed for posterity <hi>That although there was such a thing as a Descent many times, yet the King of England ever held the greatest assurance of their Titles when it was declared by Parliament:</hi> And Sir, your Oath, the manner of your Coronation doth
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36403:40"/> shew plainly, that thh Kings of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> although its true by the Law, the next person in blood is designed: yet if there were just cause to refuse him, the people of England might do it. For there is a Contract and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain made between the King and his people, and your Oath is taken, and certainly Sir, the Bond is reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall, for as you are the liege Lord, so they liege Subjects, and wee know very well that hath been so much spoken of, <hi>Ligantis est duplex.</hi> This wee know now, the one tye, the one Bond, is the Bond of perfection which is dew from the Soveraigne, the other is the Bond of subjection, that is due from the Subject Sir, if this Bond be once broken, farewell Soveraignty, <hi>Subjectio trahit</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>These things may not bee denyed Sir, I speake it th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:36403:40"/> rather, and I pray God it may work upon your heart, that you may be sensible of your miscarriages; For whether you have been, as by your Office you ought to be a Protector of England, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyer of <hi>England,</hi> let all <hi>England</hi> judg, or all the world that hath loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked upon it Sir, though you have it by Inheritance, in the way that is spoken of, yet it must not be denyed that your Office was an Office of Trust, and an Office of the highest Trust lodged in any single person; For as you were the grand <hi>Administrator of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> and others were as your <hi>delegates</hi> to see it done throughout your Realms, if your great Office were to do Justice, and preserve your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from wrong, and instead of doing that, you will be the great wrong-doer your self; if instead of being a <hi>Conservater of the peace,</hi> you wil be <hi>the Grand disturber of the peace,</hi> sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36403:41"/> this is contrary to your office, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to your Trust. Now sir, if it be an off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inheritancne, as you speak of your Title by Descent, let all men know, that great offices are seizable and forfeitable, as if you had it but for a year, and for your life, therefore sir, it wil concern you to take into your serious consideration your great mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages in this kind.</p>
               <p>Truly Sir, I shall not particularize the many miscarriages of your Reign whatsoever, they are famously known it had been happy for the Kingdome, and happy for you too, if it had not been so much known, and so much felt, as the storie of your miscarriages must needs be, and hath been already.</p>
               <p>Sir, that that we are now upon by the command of the highest Court hath been and is, to try and judge you for great offences of yours. Sir, the charge hath called you <hi>Tyrant, a Traytor a Murtherer, and a publique enemy to the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:36403:41"/> Commonwealth of England.</hi> Sir, it had been well, if that any of al these terms might rightly and justly have been spared, if any one of them at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Ha?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord pres,</speaker>
               <p>Truly sir, we have been told <hi>Rex est dum bene Regit, Tyranrus qui populum apprimei,</hi> and if so be that be the difinition of a Tyrant, then see how you come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hort of it in your Actions, whether the highest Tyrant by that way of <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> and that you have sought for to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, and that you have sought to put, you were putting upon the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whether that was not as high an Act of Tirannie as anie of your prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors were guiltie of, nay, many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees beyond it.</p>
               <p>Sir, the term Traytor cannot be spared, we shall easily agree it must denote and suppose a breach of Trust, and it must suppose it to be done by a superior, and therefore sir, as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:36403:42"/> of England, might have incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that respecting you, if they had been truly guilty of it, as to the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Law: so on the other side, when you did break your ttust to the Kingdom, you did break your trust to your superior, for the Kingdome is that for which you were trusted: and therefore sir, for this breach of trust when you are called to account, you are called to account by your superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, <hi>Minimus ad Majorem in judicium vocat.</hi> And Sir, the people of <hi>England</hi> cannot be so far wanting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, which God having dealt so mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculously and gloriously for, they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving power in their hands and their great enemy they must proceed to do Justice to themselves and to you, for sir, the Court could heartily desire, that you would lay your hand upon your heart and consider what you have done amiss, that you would endeavor to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e your peace
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:36403:42"/> with God. Truly sir, These are your high crimes, Tyranny and Treason</p>
               <p>There is a third thing too if those had not been, and that is Murther▪ which is laid to your charge. All the bloody Murthers, that have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted since this time that the div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sion was betwixt you and your peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> must be layd to your charge, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have been acted or commited in thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> late wars: sir it is an heinou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and crying sin; and truly Sir, if an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man wil ask us what punishment i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> due to a Murtherer, let Gods Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let mans Law speak. Sir, I wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> presume that you are so well read i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> scripture as to know what God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self hath said concerning the sheddin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of mans blood, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. <hi>Numb.</hi> 35 wiil tel you what the punishmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is, and which this Court in behalf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Kingdome are sensible of, of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> innocent blood that has been
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:36403:43"/> shed, whereby indeed the Land stands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>till defiled with that blood, and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Text hath it, <hi>Jt can no way bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leansed, but with the shedding of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lood of him that shed the blood:</hi> Sir, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e know no D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>spensation from this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lood in that Commandment, <hi>Thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>halt do no murther;</hi> we do not know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut that it ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ends to Kings as well as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the meanest Peasants, the meanest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the people, the command is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ersall. Sir, Gods Law forbids it, Mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw forbids it, nor do we know tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here is any manner of exception, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven in mans laws, for the punishment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f murther in you. 'Tis true, that in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he case of Kings every privat hand was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or to put forth it sel e to this work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or their reformation and punishment. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut Sir, the people represented having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower in their hands, had there been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one wilful act of murther by you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommitted, had power to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ented you, and to punish you for it.
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36403:43"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36403:44"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36403:44"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36403:45"/>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:36403:45"/> that you would hear me concerning those great imputations that you have laid unto my charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord president.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you must give me now leave to go on, for I am not far from your sentence, and your time is now past.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>But I shall desire you wil hear me a few words to you, for truly what ever Sentence you wil put upon me, in respect of those heavy impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations that I see by your speech you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve put upon me, Sir, it is very true that—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord Pres.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, <hi>J</hi> must put you in mind, sir, I would not willingly at this time especiallie, interrupt you in any thing you have to say that is proper for us to admit of; but sir, you have not owned us as a court, and you look upon us as a sort of people met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and we know what language we receive from your partie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>I know nothing of that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:36403:46"/>
               <speaker>Lord pres.</speaker>
               <p>You dis-avow us as a Court, and therefore for you to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress your self to us, not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg us as a Court to judg of what you say, it is not to be permitted; and the truth is, all along from the first time you were pleased to dis avow and dis-owne us, the Court needed not to have heard you one word; for unless they be acknowledged a Court, and engaged, it is not proper for you to speak, sir we have given you too much liberty alreadie, and admitted of too much delay, and we may not admit of any further; were it proper for us to do we should hear you freeely, and we should not have declined to have heard you at large, what you could have said or proved on your behalf, whether to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally excusing, or for in part exen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing those great and Hainous Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that in whole or in part are laid upon you. But sir, I shal trouble
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:36403:46"/> you no longer, your sins are so large a dimension, that if you do but seriously think of them, they will drive you to a sad consideration, and they may improve in you a sad and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rious repentance. And that the Court doth heartily wish that you may be so penitent for what you have done amiss, that God may have mercy at least wise upon your better part. Truly Sir, for the other, it is our parts and duties to do that, that the Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rescribes, we are not here <hi>Ius dare,</hi> but <hi>Jus dicere;</hi> We cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful of what the Scriptures tels us, <hi>For to acquit the guilty, is of equall ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination as to condemn the innocent,</hi> we may not acquit the guilty; what sentence the Law affirms to a traytor, tyrant, a Murtherer, and a publique Enemy to the Countrey, that sentence you are now to hear read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto you and that is the sentence of the Court.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:36403:47"/>
               <p>The <hi>Lord President</hi> commands the sentence to be read, make an O Yes, and command Silence while the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is read:</p>
               <p>O Yes made, silence commanded.</p>
               <p>The Clerk read the sentence, which was drawn up in pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whereas the Commons of</hi> England <hi>in Parliament have appointed them an high Court of Justice for the trying of</hi> Charls Stuart <hi>King of England, before whom hee had been three times convented, and at the first time a Charge of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and other Ceimes and Misdem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anors was read in the behalf of the Kingdom of England, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the Clerk read the Charge.</p>
               <p>Which Charg being read unto hm as aforesaid, he the said <hi>Charge Stuart,</hi> was required to give his answer, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e refused so to do, and so expres't the several passages at his tryall in refusing to answer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For all which Treasons and Crimes
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:36403:47"/> this Court doth adjudg, that the said</hi> Charls Stuart, <hi>as a Tyrant, traytor, Murtherer, and publique Enemie, shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e put to death, by the severing his Head from his Bodie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the sentence read, the Lord president said.</p>
               <p>This sentence now read and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and it is this Act, Sentence, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and resolution of the whole Court.</p>
               <p>Here the Court stood up, (and assen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g to what the president said.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Wil you hear me a word sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord pres.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you are not to be heard after the sentence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King</speaker>
               <p>No sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lord pres.</speaker>
               <p>No sir, by your favor sit: Guard withdraw your prsoner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>I may speak after the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce—</p>
               <p>By your favor sir, I may speak after the sentence ever.</p>
               <p>By your favor hold the sentence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir.—</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:36403:48"/>
               <p>I say sir, I do—</p>
               <p>I am not suffered for to speak, expect what Justice other people wil have.</p>
               <p>O Yes, All manner of persons that have any thing else to do, are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part at this time, and to give their attendance in the painted Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to which place this Court doth forthwith adjourn it self.</p>
               <p>Then the Court rose, and the King went with his Guard to Sir <hi>Robert Cottons,</hi> and from thence to White-Hall.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A List of the Names of the Judges and Officers of the High Court of Iustice. which sate at the tryal of the King in the great Hall, at Westminster, Ian. <hi>20 1648.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>SErjeant <hi>Bradshuw</hi> Lord</item>
               <item>President.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> Lievt. General.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Ireton,</hi> Com. General</item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Hardress Waller</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Harrison.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:36403:48"/>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Whaley:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Pride.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Ewer:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Gray</hi> of Groby.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>John D' Anvers,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Maleverer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Bowcher.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Henningham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alderman Pennington</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Martin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Purefoy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Bark stead.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Tomlinson.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Blackston.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Millington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Gregory Norton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Harvey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Ven.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alderman Audrews.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Crawley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Burrel</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Stapley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Downs.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:36403:49"/>
               <item>Lievt General <hi>Hamond</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Love.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Norton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master. <hi>Potter:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Garland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>William Constable.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Ludlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Hutchinson.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Michell Livesey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Dixwell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Fleetwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Mayne,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>James Temple:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Blagrave.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Titchbourne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Ronet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Scroop.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Lilbourne:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Deane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Okey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Huson.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lievt. Collonel <hi>Goffe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Corn Holand.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Carem.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:36403:49"/>
               <item>Master <hi>John Jones.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Miles Corbet,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Francis Allen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Perigrin Pelham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Moore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Eldner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Edwards.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Master <hi>Clement.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonel <hi>Woggon.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Officers of the <hi>COƲRT.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>D. <hi>Dorisl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w,</hi> Mr. Justice <hi>Ask,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors for the Commonwealth.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Cook</hi> Solicitor General.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Broughten,</hi> Mr. <hi>Phelps,</hi> Clarks to the Court.</item>
               <item>Serjeant <hi>Danhy,</hi> Mace Bearer.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Humphry</hi> Sword Bearer.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>King</hi> Cryer of the Court.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:36403:50"/>
            <head>Other matters relating to the procee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dings in the tryal of Charls Stuart lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King of England. Resolutions of the Court in the painted Chamber: Lunae Ian. <hi>22. 1648.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis day the King being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from the Bar of the High Court of Justice, The Commissioners of the said Court of high Justice sate private in the Painted Chamber; and considered of the Kings carriage upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the saturday before, and of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had then passed, and fully approved of what the Lord President had done and said in the mannaging of the business of that day as agreeing to their sense: and perceiving what the King aymed at, <hi>viz</hi> so birng in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion if he could the jurisdiction of the Court, and the authority thereof, whereby they sate, and considering that in the interim he had not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:36403:50"/> them in any sort to be a Court, or his Judges, and through their sides intended to wound (if he might be permitted) the supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Commons of England</hi> in their Representative the <hi>Commons</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled in Parliament, After advice with their Council learned in both Laws, and mature deliberation had of the matter:</p>
            <p>Resolved that the King should not be suffred to argue the Courts juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or that which constituted them a Court of which debate they had not proper Cognizance, nor could they, being a derivative Iudge of that supreme Court which made them Iudges, from which there was no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal: And did therefore order and direct, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ordred that in case the King shal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain offer to dispute the authority of the court, the L. President do let him know, that the Court have taken into
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:36403:51"/> consideration his demands of the last day; and that he ought to rest satisfied with this answer: that the Commons of England assembled in parliament, have constituted this Court, whose power may not, nor should be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be disputed by him.</p>
            <p>That in case the King shall refuse to answer or acknowledg the Court, the Lord president do let him know that the Court wil take it as a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntumacy, and that it shal be so recorded.</p>
            <p>That in case he shal offer to answer with a saving notwithstanding of his pretended prerogative above the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction of the Court.</p>
            <p>That the Lord President do in the name of the Court refuse his protest, and require his positive answer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he wil own the Court or not.</p>
            <p>That in case the King shall demand, a copy of the charge, that he shal then declare his intention to answer and that declaring his intention a copy be granted to him.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:36403:51"/>
            <p>That in case the King shal stil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in his contempt, the Lord President do give command to the Clerk to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the King in the name of the Court in these words following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Charls Stuarr <hi>King of England, you are accused in the behalf of the people of England of divers high crimes and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, which charge hath been read unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Court requires you to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> positive answer to confess or denie the charge, having determined that you ought to answer the same:</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Hardresse VValler.</hi> Col. <hi>Harri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> Col. <hi>Dean,</hi> Com. Gen. <hi>Jreton,</hi> Col. <hi>Okey,</hi> are appointed to consider of the time and place for the execution of the King according to his sentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the High Court of Justice.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:36403:52"/>
            <head>Painted Chamber, Lunae Jan. <hi>29. 1648.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>UPon Report made from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for considering of the time and place for the executing of the judgment against the King, That the said Committee have resolved, That the open street before <hi>Whitehall</hi> is a fit place, And that the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee conceive it fit that the King be there executed the morrow. The King having notice thereof. The Court ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paoved thereof, and Ordered a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to be drawn for that purpose, and agreed unto, and ordered it to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grossed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Painted Chamber. <hi>30.</hi> Ian. <hi>1648.</hi> The Commissioners met, And</head>
            <p>ORdered, that M. <hi>Marshall,</hi> M. <hi>Nye,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caryll,</hi> Mr. <hi>Salway,</hi> and M. <hi>Dell,</hi> be desired to attend the King
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36403:52"/> to administer to him those spirituall helps as should be sutable to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent condition: And Lieut. Col. <hi>Goffe</hi> is desired forthwith to repaire unto them for that purpose.</p>
            <p>Who did so, but after informed the Court, that the King being acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith refused to confer with them, expressing that he would not be troubled with them.</p>
            <p>Ordered, That the Scaffold upon which the King is to be executed, bee covered with black.</p>
            <p>The Warrant for executing the King being accordingly delivered to those pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties to whom the same wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> directed, execution was done upon him according to the tenour of the warrant about two of the clock in the afternoon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:36403:53"/>
            <head>King <hi>Charls</hi> his speech made upon the Scaffold at White-Hall-Gate imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before his Execution, Tuesday, Ian. <hi>30.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ABout ten in the morning the King was brought from St. <hi>James's,</hi> walking on foot, through the park, with a Regiment of foot, part before, and part behind him, with Colours flying, Drums beating, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s private guard of partizans, with some of his Gentlemen before, and some behinde bare-headed. Dr. <hi>Iuxon</hi> next him, and Colonel <hi>Thomlinson,</hi> who had the charge of him, talking with the King bare-headed from the park, up the stairs into the Gallery, and so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the Cabinet Chamber, where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sed to lie, where he continued at his Devotion refusing to dine, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:36403:53"/> taken the Sacrament, only about an hour before he came forth, he drank a glass of Claret wine, and eat a peece of bread about twelve at noon.</p>
            <p>From thence he was accompani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by Dr. <hi>Iuxon,</hi> Col. <hi>Thomlinson,</hi> and other Officers, formerly appointed to attend him, and the private Guard of Partizans, with Musketiers on each side, through the Banqueting house. adjoyning, to which the Scaffold was erected, between Whitehall-gate, and the Gate leading into the gallery from <hi>S. James's:</hi> the Scaffold was hung round with black, and the floor co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with black, and the Ax and Block laid in the middle of the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. There were divers companies of Foot, and troops of Horse placed on the one side of the Scaffold towards <hi>Kings street,</hi> and on the other side to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Charing Cross,</hi> and the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of people that came to be spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators very great.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:36403:54"/>
            <p>The King being come upon the Scaffold, looked very earnestly upon the block, and asked Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> if there were no higher, and then speak thus, directing his Speech chiefly to Col. <hi>Thomlinson.</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>I Shall be very little heard of any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy here, I shall therefore speak a word unto you here: indeed I could hold my peace very well if I did not think that holding my peace would make some men think, that I did sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the guilt, as wel as to the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ishment, but I think it is my duty to God first, and to my Countrey, for to clear my self both as an honest man, a good King, and a good Christian. I shall begin first with my innocency, introth I think it not very needful for me to insist long upon this, for all the world knows that I never did begin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> War with the two houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, and I call God to witness, to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:36403:54"/> whom <hi>I</hi> must shortly make an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that I never did intend for to incroach upon their priviledges, they began upon me, it is the Militia they began upon, they confest that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia was mine, but they thought it fit for to have it from me, and to be short, if any body wil look to the dates of Commissions, of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions and mine, and likewise to the Declarations, wil see clearly that they began these unhappy Troubles, not I: so that as the guilt of these enormous crimes that are laid against me, <hi>I</hi> hope in God that God wil clear me of, <hi>J</hi> wil not, <hi>I</hi> am in charity, God forbid that I should lay it upon the two ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Parliament, there is no necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of either, <hi>J</hi> hope they, are fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this guilt: for <hi>I</hi> do believe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ill instruments between them an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me, has beene the chiefe caus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of all this Blood-shed, so that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way of speaking, as I finde m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:36403:55"/> self clear of this, I hope, and pray God, that they may too: yet for all this, God forbid that I should bee so ill a Christian, as not to say, that Gods Judgments are just upon mee: Many times hee does pay justice by unjust sentence, that is ordinary; I will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly say this, That an unjust Sentence that I suffered for to take effect,<note n="*" place="margin">Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</note> is punished now by an unjust Sentence upon me, that is so as I have said, to shew you that I am an innocent man.</p>
               <p>Now for to shew you that I am a good Christian I hope there is a good man that wil bear me witness,<note place="margin">Pointing to <hi>Dr.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uxon.</note> that I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given all the world, and even those in particular that have been the chiefe causers of my death; who they are, God knowes, I doe not desire to know, I pray God forgive them. But this is not all, my Charity must go farther, I wish
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36403:55"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36403:56"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36403:56"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36403:57"/>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:36403:57"/> Kingdom and your own salvations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dr. <hi>Juxon.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Will your Majesty, though it may be very well known your Majesties affections to Religion, yet it may be expected that you should say somwhat for the worlds sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>J thank you very hartily, my Lord, for that J had almost forgotten it, introth sirs, my Conscience in Religion</hi> I <hi>think it is very wel known to all the World, and therefore</hi> I <hi>declare before you all, that</hi> I <hi>dye a Christian, according to the profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Church of England as</hi> I <hi>found it left me by my father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to D. <hi>Iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>and this honest man</hi> I <hi>think will witness it. Then turning to the Officers said: sirs excuse me for this same,</hi> I <hi>have a good cause, and</hi> I <hi>have a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God,</hi> I <hi>will say no more. Then tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Colonel</hi> Hacker, <hi>he said; Tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> care they do not put me to pain, and si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this, and it please you; But then a Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tleman
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:36403:58"/> coming near the Ax, the King said, take heed of the Ax, pray take heed of the Ax, then the King speaking to the Executioner, said, J shall say but very short Prayers, and when</hi> I <hi>thrust out my hands—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then the King called to Doctor</hi> Jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>for his Night-Cap, and having put it on, he said to the Executioner, Does my hair trouble you? who desired him to put it all under his Cap, which the King did accordingly by the help of the Executioner and the Bishop: Then the King turning to Doctor</hi> Juxon. <hi>said,</hi> I <hi>have a good Cause, and a gracious God on my side.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Juxon,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is but one Stage more, This Stage is turbulent and troublesome, it is a short one: But you may consider, it will soon carry you a very great way, it will carry you from Earth to Heaven; and there you shall find a great deal of cordial joy and comfort:</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:36403:58"/>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>I <hi>go from a corruptible to an incorruptible Crown, where no distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance can be no disturbance in the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Juxon.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You are exchanged from a Temporal to an eternall Crown a good exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King then said to the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, is my hair well? Then the King tooke of his Cloak and his George, giving his George to Doctor</hi> Jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>saying, Remember— Then the King put of his dou.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">It is thought for to give it to the Prince.</note>
                  <hi>Act, and being in his Wast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat, put his Cloak on again, then looked upon the block said to the executioner, you must set it fast.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Executioner.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is fast Sir.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When</hi> I <hi>put my hands out this way, stretching them out, then—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After that having said two or three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ords, as hee stood, to himself, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ands and eyes lift up, immediately stooping down, laid his Neck <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:36403:59"/> the other; and then the executioner again, putting his hair under his Cap, the King said thinking he had been going to strike stay for the sign.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Executioner.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I wll, and it please your Majesty,</p>
               <p>And after a very little pause, the King stretching forth his hands, the Executioner at one blow severed his head from his body, the head being off, the Executioner held it up, and shewed it to the people, which done, it was with the body put in a Coffin, covered with black Velvet for that purpose, and conveyed into his Lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings there: and from thence it was carried to his house at <hi>S. Iames's,</hi> where his body was put in a Coffin of Lead, laid there to be seen by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and about a fortnight after it was carried to <hi>Windsor,</hi> accompanied with the Duke of <hi>Lenox,</hi> the Marquess of <hi>Hartford,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Southampton</hi> and Doctor <hi>Iuxon,</hi> late Bishop of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:36403:59"/>
                  <hi>London,</hi> and others, and interred in the Chappel Royal, in the Vault with <hi>King Henry</hi> the eight, having onely this Inscription upon the Coffin, <hi>Charls, King of England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <q>Sic transit Gloria Mundi.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:36403:60"/>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:36403:60"/>
            <head>PRAYERS Used by His MAIESTY, In the time of His SUFFERINGS: Delivered to Doctor <hi>Juxon,</hi> Bishop of <hi>London,</hi> immediately before his <hi>Death. ALSO, A</hi> Letter from the Prince.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer in time of Captivity.</head>
               <p>O Powerful and Eternal God to whom nothing is so great, that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:36403:61"/> it may resist, or so small, that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, look upon my miserie with thine eye of mercie, and let thine infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite power vouchsafe to limit out som proportion of deliverance unto me, as to thee shal seem most convenient, let not injurie, O Lord, triumph over me, and let my faults by thy hand be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and make not my unjust ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the Ministers of thy Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tice, but yet my God, if in thy wisdome this be the aptest chastisement for my unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusable transgressions, if this ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful bondage be fittest for my over-high desires; if the pride of my not enough humble heart be thus to be broken; O Lord I yeild unto thy wil, and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully embrace what sorrow thou wilt have me suffer: onely thus much let me crave of thee, Let my craving O Lord, be accepted of, since it even pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from thee, that by thy goodness which is thy self, thou wilt suffer som beam of thy Majestie so to shine in my
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:36403:61"/> minde, that I, who acknowledg it my noblest title to be thy Creature, may stil in my greatest afflictions depend constantly upon thee. Let Calamitie be the exercise, but not the overthrow of my vertue. O let not their prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling power be to my destruction. And if it be thy wil that they more &amp; more vex me with punishment; yet O Lord never let their wickedness have such a hand, but that I may stil carrie a pure minde, and steadfast resolution euer to serve thee, without fear or presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet with that humble confidence which may best please thee; so that at the last I may come to thy Eternall Kingdom through the merits of thy Son our Sauior Jesus Christ. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another Prayer.</head>
               <p>ALmighty and most merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, look down upon me thy
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:36403:62"/> unworthy servant who here prostrate my self at the Foot Stool of thy Throne of Grace. <hi>But look upon Mee, O Father, through the Mediation and in the Merits of Iesus Christ, in whom thou art only wel pleased; for of my self</hi> I <hi>am not worthie to stand before thee, or to speak with My unclean lips to Thee, most holie and eternal God, for as in sin</hi> I <hi>was conceived and born, so likewise</hi> I <hi>have broken all thy Commandments by my sinful motions, unclean thoughts, evil words, and wicked works, omitting many duties</hi> I <hi>ought to do, and committing many vices which thou hast forbidden under pain of thy heavie displeasure, as for my sins O Lord, they are innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wherefore</hi> I <hi>stand here liable to all the Miseries in this life, and everlasting Torments in that to come, if thou shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest deal with me according to my deserts. J consess, O Lord, that it is thy mercy which endureth for ever, and thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion which never failes, which is the</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:36403:62"/> cause that <hi>I</hi> have not been long ago consumed, but with thee there is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and plentious Redempton; in the multitude therefore of thy Mercies and by the Merits of Jesus Christ, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thy Divine Majestie, that thou wouldest not enter into judgment with thy Servant, nor be extreme, to mark what is done amiss, but be thou merciful unto me, and wash away all my sins with that precious blood that my Saviour shed for me, and I beseech thee, O Lord not only to wash away all my sins, but also to purge my heart by thy holy Spirit, from the dross of my natural corruption; and as Thou doest add days to my life, so, good Lord I beseech thee, to add repentance to my days, that when I have past this mortal life, I may be partaker of thy everlasting Kingdome, through the Merits of Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:36403:63"/>
               <head>A Prayer and Confession, made in, and for the times of affliction,</head>
               <p>ALmightie and most merciful fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it is only thy goodness that admits of our imperfect prayers, and the knowledg that thy mercies are infinite, which can gives us any hope of thy accepting or granting them: so it is our bounden and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie dutie to confess our sins freely unto thee, and of all men living, I have most need, most reason, so to do, no man having been so much obliged by thee, no man more grievously offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thee, that degree of knowledg which thou hast given me, adding likewise to the guilt of my transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. For was it through ignorance, that I suffered innocent blood to be shed by a false pretended way of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice? or that I permitted a wrong way of thy Worship to be set up in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> and injured the Bishops in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland?
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:36403:63"/> O no; but with shame and griefe I confess, that I therein follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the perswasions of worldly wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, forsaking the dictates of a right informed Conscience: Wherefore, O Lord, I have no excuse to make, no hope left, but in the multitude of thy Mercies; for I know my repentance weak, and my prayers faultie: Grant therefore, merciful Father, so to streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my repentance, and amend my prayers, that thou mayest clear the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay for thine own Mercies; to which, O let thy Justice at last give place, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a speedie end to my deserved affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. In the mean time give me pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to endure, Constancie against Temptations, and a discerning Spirit to chuse, what is best for thy Church and people which thou hast commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to my Charge. Grant this, O most merci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul Father, for thy Son Iesus Christ's sake, our Saviour. <hi>Amen,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:36403:64"/>
               <head>A Prayer in time of imminent danger.</head>
               <p>O Most mercifull Father, though my sins are so many and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, that I may rather expect the effects of thy anger, then so great a deliverance, as to free Mee from My present great danger; yet O Lord, since thy Mercies are over all thy works, and thou never failest to relieve all those who with humble and unfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentance come to thee for suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, it were to multiply, not diminish my transgressions, to despair of thy heavenly favor: Wherefore I humbly desire thy divine Majesty, that thou wilt not onely pardon all my sins, but also free Mee out of the hands, and protect mee from the malice of my cruel enemies. But if thy wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my hainous offences will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways be satisfied, then by suffering
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:36403:64"/> me to fall under my present afflictious thy will be done; yet with humble importunity I do, and shal never leave to implore the assistance of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Spirit, that my cause, as I am thy Vicegerent, may not suffer through my weakness or want of courage. O Lord, so strengthen and en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighten all the faculties of my minde, that with clearness I may shew forth thy truth and manfully endure this bloody try all, that so my sufferings here may no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> onely glorifie thee, but likewise be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> furtherance to my salvation hereafte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Grant this, O merciful Father, for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> sake, who suffered for me, even Iesus Christ the righteous. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:36403:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>His Majesties</hi> REASONS AGAINST The Iurisdiction of the High Court of Justice, which He intended to deliver in writing, on Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <hi>Ian</hi> 22. 1648.</head>
               <p>HAving already made my prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations not onely against the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legality of this pretended Court, but also that no earthly power can ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stly call me, who am your King, in question as a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>linquent; I would not any more open my mouth upon this occasion more then to referre my selfe to what I have spoken, were <hi>J</hi> alone in this case concerned:
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:36403:65"/> But the dutie <hi>I</hi> owe to God in the preservation of the true Liberty of my people, will not suffer me at this time to bee silent. For how can any Freeborn Subject of <hi>England</hi> call Life, or any thing bee posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owne, if power without right, daily make new, and abro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gate the Old Fundamental Lawes of the Land, which <hi>J</hi> now take to bee the present case. Wherefore when I came hither, I expected that you would have endeavoured to have satisfied me concerning these grounds which hinder mee to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to your pretended impeachment; but since that I see that nothing I can say will move you to it though Negatives are not so na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally proved as Affirmatives, yet I will shew you the Reason, why I am confident you cannot judge mee, nor indeed the meanest man in <hi>England;</hi> for, I will not, like
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:36403:66"/> you, without shewing a reason, see<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to impose a beliefe upon my Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jects.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Hereabout I was stopt, and not suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to speake any more concerning reason.</note>There is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding just against any man, but wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is warranted eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by Gods Laws, or the Municipal laws of the Countrey where he lives. Now I am most confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that this days proceeding cannot be warrante by God's Law; for, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the contrary, the autority of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto Kings is clearly warranted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd strictly commanded both in the Old and New Testament; which if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enied, I am ready instantly to prove; And for the question now in hand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here it is said, <hi>That where the word of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King is, there is Power, and who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay say unto him, What doest Thou?</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cles, chap. 8. ver. 4. Then for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes of this Land, I am no
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:36403:66"/> less confident that no Learned Law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer wil affirm that an Impeachmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can lie, against the King, they all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Name; and one of their Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims is, <hi>That the King can do no wrong▪</hi> Besides, The Law upon which you ground your proceedings, must either be old, or new, if old, shew it, if new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tel what authority warranted by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fundamental Laws of the Land hath made it, and when. But how th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> House of Commons can erect a Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Judicature, which was never on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it self, as is wel known to all Law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yers, I leave to God and the Worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to judge: And it were full a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> strange, that they should pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make Laws without King o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lords House, to any that hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heard speake of the Laws of <hi>Englan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>And admitting, but not granti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the People of <hi>Englands</hi> Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sion could grant your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ete<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded Power, I see nothing y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:36403:67"/> can shew for that, for certainly you never asked the question of the tenth man of the Kingdom, and in this way you manifestly wrong even the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest Ploughman, if you demand not his free consent? nor can you pretend any colour for this pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission without the consent at least of the major part of every man in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, of whatsoever qualitie, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which I am sure you never went about to seek: so far are you from having it. Thus you see that <hi>J</hi> sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> not for my own right alone, as I am your King, but also for the true Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all my Subjects, which consists not in sharing the power of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but in living under such Law, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch a Government as may give, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elves the best assurance of their lives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd propriety of their goods. Nor in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is must or do I forget the Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of hoth Houses of Parliament, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich this day; proceeding doth not
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:36403:67"/> onely violate, but likewise occasio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the greatest breach of their Publike Faith that I believe ever was heard of, with which I am far from charging the two Houses; for all the pretended Crimes laid aginst me, bare date long hefore this late Treatie at <hi>Newport,</hi> in which I having concluded as much as in mee lay, and hopefully expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the two Houses agreement thereunto, I was suddenly surprized▪ and hurried from thence as a Prisoner, upon which account I am against my wil brought hither, where since I am come, I cannot but, to my power, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ancient Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom, together with my own just right; then for any thing I can see the higher House is totally excluded.</p>
               <p>And for the House of Commons, it is too well known that the majo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part of them, are deteined or deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red from sitting, so as if I had no other, this were sufficient for me to protes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:36403:68"/> against the lawfulness of your preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Court. Besides all this, the peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Kingdom is not the least in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>houghts, and what hopes of settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is there so long as power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aigns without rule of Law. changing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he whole frame of that Government <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nder which this Kingdom hath flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ished for many hundred yeers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or wil <hi>J</hi> say what wil fall out in case <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his lawless unjust proceeding against me do go on, and believe it, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England wil not thank you for this change, for they wil remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how happie they have been of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate yeers under the Reign of Q. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> the King my Father, and my self, until the beginning of these un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie troubles; and will have cause to doubt that they shall never be so happie under any new. And by this time it will be too sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly evident, that the Arms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> took up were onely to defend the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:36403:68"/> fundamentall Laws of this Kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> against those who have supposed m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power hath totally changed the anci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent Government.</p>
               <p>Thus having shewed you briefly th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Reasons, why I cannot submit to you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pretended authority without viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the trust which <hi>I</hi> have from Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the welfare of my people: <hi>I</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from you either clear Reasons t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> convince my judgment, shewing m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that I am in an error, and then truly <hi>J</hi> wil readily Answer, or that you wil withdraw your proceedings.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>This J intended to speak in</hi> Westmin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster Hall <date>
                        <hi>on Monday</hi> 22. Jannarie <hi>but against reason was hindred t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> shew my Reasons.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:36403:69"/>
               <head>A Copie of a Letter which was sent from the Prince to the King, Dated from the <hi>Hague</hi> Ian. <hi>23. 1648.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAving no means to come to the knowledg of your Majesties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent condition, but such as I receive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom the Prints, or which is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertaine, Report. I have sent thi Bearer <hi>Seamour,</hi> to wait upos Your Majesty, I doe not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ray for your Majestie according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Dutie, but shall always be readie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o do all which shall be in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower, to deserve that blessing which
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:36403:69"/> I now hambly beg of Your Majesty upon</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Majesties Most humble and most obedient Son and Servant,</hi> Charls.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Hague,</hi>
                     <date>Jan. 22. 1648.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>The Superscription was thus,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>For the King.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:36403:70"/>
               <head>Monday 29. <hi>January</hi> 1648. true Relation of the KINGS Speech to the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Glocester,</hi> the day before his death.</head>
               <p>HIs Children being come to meet him, he first gave his blessing to the Lady <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and bad her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to tel her Brother <hi>Iames,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver she should see him, that it was his Fathers last desire, that hee should no more look upon <hi>Charls</hi> as his eldest Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her only, lout be obedient unto him, as his Soveraign; and that they should love one another, and forgive their Fathers Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: Then said the King to her, Sweet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art, you'l forget this: No, said shee, <hi>I</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all never forget it while <hi>I</hi> live; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uring forth abundance of tears, pro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ised him to write down the particulars.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:36403:70"/>
               <p>Then the King taking the Duke of <hi>Glocester</hi> upon his Knee, said, Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart, Now they will cut off thy Fathers Head; upon which words the Child loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed very stedfastly on him, Mark Child what J say, they will cut off my head, and perhaps make thee a King: But mark what <hi>I</hi> say, you must not be a King, so long as your Brothers, <hi>Charls</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> do live: For they wil cut off your Brothers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eads, when they can cath them, and cut off thy Head too at the last: and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> charge you, do not be made a King by them. At which the Child sighing, said I wil be torn in pieces first. Which fulling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o unexspectedly from one so young, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade the King rejoyce exceedingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:36403:71"/>
               <head>Another Relation from the Lady <hi>Elisa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> own hand.</head>
               <p>VVHat the King said to me the nine and twentieth of Ian. 1648. being the last time I had the happiness to see him, he told me, hee was glad I was come, and although he had not time to say much, yet som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what he had to say to me, which he had not to another, or leave in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, because he feared their Crueltie was such, as that they would not hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> permitted him to write to me. He wished me not to grieve and torment my self for him, for that would be a glorious death that he should die; it being for the Laws and Liberties of this Land, and for maintaining the true Protestant Religion: He bid me read Bishop <hi>Andrews</hi> Sermons, <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Ecclesiasticall Politie,</hi> and Bishop <hi>Lauds</hi> book against <hi>Fisher,</hi> which would ground me against Poperie. He
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:36403:71"/> told me, he had forgiven all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and hoped God would forgive them also; and commanded us, and the rest of my Brothers and sisters to forgive them. He bid me tel my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That his thoughts had never strayed from her, and that his love should be the same to the last. Withal, hee commanded me and my Brother to be obedient to her. And bid me send his blessing to the rest of my Brothers and Sisters, with Commendation to al his Friends. So after he had given me his blessing, I took my leave.</p>
               <p>Further, He commanded us all to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give those people, but never to trust them; for they had been most false to him, and to those that gave him power and he feared also to their own souls: and desired me not to grieve for him, for he should die a Martyr, and that he doubted not but the Lord would settle his throne upon his Son, and that we should be all happier then we
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:36403:72"/> could have expected to have been, if he had lived. With many other things which at present I cannot remember.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Elizabeth.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Relation from the Lady <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe King said to the Duke of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> that he would say nothing to him, but what was for the good of his soul: He told him, that he heard the Army intended to make him King; but it was a thing not for him to take upon him, if he regarded the welfar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his Soul, for he had two Brothers before him, and therefore commanded him upon his blessing, never to accept of it, unless it redounded lawfully up him, and commanded him to fear the Lord, and he would provide for him.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36403:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>